Michael McLoughlin

Professional Profile

Overview

I have worked as a technical writer for 15 years for some of the world's leading multi-national security, financial and networking infrastructure companies with branches in Belfast.

Puppet

At Puppet, I use Oxygen XML editor to write DITA and Markdown content for Puppet's network security product, Remediate. In addition, I create instructional videos using Screenflow for documentation and marketing purposes. I also work with Puppet's documentation repositories on GitHub, DITA Open Toolkit plugins, writing toolchain.

Proofpoint

At Proofpoint, I developed web-based training courses using Storyline, and short instructional videos using Camtasia for several email gateway and email fraud prevention products. In addtion, I used Pendo to develop context-sensitive help for Proofpoint's SME email gateway offering, Proofpoint Essentials.

IBM

At IBM, I was Belfast site lead for an Information Development team spread between Belfast, the US and Canada. I produced API and developer documentation and training materials for IBM's flagship security intelligence platform, QRadar. I used DITA and Framemaker to write application development tutorials for internal and external consumption. As site lead for documentation, I mentored team members, and managed the documentation design and production processes.

NYSE Technologies

At NYSE, I was in charge of all documentation for the market leading financial information exchange engine and its associated products. I produced documentation in PDF and HTML webhelp formats for non-technical users as well as for developers using Madcap Flare.

Openwave Systems

At Openwave, I developed and maintained documentation for complex telecommunications gateway products (service management, analytics, traffic optimization etc.) using DITA and Framemaker. As well as writing, I also project managed larger writing projects involving distributed writing teams in Belfast, the US and India.

Latens Systems

Prior to my engagement, Latens had no professional documentation support. I was tasked to help set documentation standards and procedures for the company. I worked with developers in Belfast and Hyderabad to develop help systems for set top box software.

Lucid Technical Documentation

At Lucid Technical Documentation I produced printed and online documentation and training materials for a variety of companies of all sizes throughout Ireland and abroad.

Education

Secondary

St Mary's CBS, Belfast

Education

Third Level Education

University College, Dublin

B.A. Hons 1988

English Literature/Italian (2:1)

M.A. 1990

Italian Literature (1st Class)

Ph.D. 1994

Contemporary Italian Literature

Professional Courses

A+ Computer Maintenance

Irish Academy of Computer Training

St Stephens Green, Dublin 2

1999-2000 Part Time

Dip. Networking and Desktop Support

Fitzwilliam Institute Ely Place, Dublin 2.

Feb-Aug 2000 Full-

time

DITA Open Toolkit

Training

Suite Solutions

15-24 June 2009

(12 hours total)

DITA Advanced Content Reuse

Comtech Services Inc

Oct-Dec 2020

(8 hours total)

Employment History

Senior Technical Writer July 2019 - Date Course Developer / **Trainer** Dec 2016 - July 2019 Information **Developer** Sept. 2014 - Dec 2016

Puppet, Inc Linenhall St. Belfast

Senior Technical Writer

Proofpoint NI Weavers Court, Belfast Technical Instructor and Course Developer

IBM United Kingdom Ltd. Queens Road, Belfast

Information Developer **IBM Security**

NYSE Technologies Adelaide St., Belfast Senior Technical Writer, Liquidity Solutions

Senior Technical Writer April 2010 - April

Openwave Systems Donegall St., Belfast Senior Technical Writer

2011

Senior Technical

April 2011 - July

Writer

2014

Latens Systems Ltd.,

Technical Writer

Nov. 2008 - April 2010

Technical Writer

Stranmillis Embankment, Belfast

Senior Technical Writer

August 2006 - Oct. 2008

Lucid Technical Documentation Ltd., Cromac St., Belfast

Senior Technical Writer, Instructional Designer

B&B Operator

Isle of Arran, Scotland

Jan 2004 - June 2006

Internet Support 2001-2003

EircomNet, EastPoint Business Pk, Dublin 3

Dial-up/Broadband support

2nd Level Support 2000-2001

L&H Speech Recognition Software,

Blackrock, Co. Dublin escalation

Bug reporting, 1st level escalation point

Desktop Support

1999

Europlus, IFSC, Dublin 2

Merchant Bank

Network and user support

Lecturer 1995-98

European Languages Dept.

University of Wales, Aberystwyth

Tutor 1989 - 1995

Italian Dept. University College

Dublin

Language Assistant 1988-1989

English Dept., Università degli

Studi di Bari

General

Software Packages	Oxygen XML editor	Camtasia	Adobe Framemaker
	Adobe Captivate	Storyline	Pendo
	Adobe Acrobat Pro	MS Word	Confluence Wiki
	MS Visio	Visual Studio Code	Madcap Flare

Docbook XSL DITA Open Toolkit MIF2GO

Markup/Scripting Languages

HTML, CSS.

XML (DITA, Docbook), XSLT (Docbook XSL/DITA Open Toolkit)

XPATH, Schematron Basic JavaScript Markdown, Asciidoc